Guide to the Robert Nathan Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- November 1982 Acquisition, 1925-1982, undated; 5.42; (16 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Fan mail, 1953-1982, undated; 7 (Box 85)
    - Fan mail (continued), 1953-1982, undated; 6 (Box 86)
    - Fan mail (continued), 1953-1982, undated; 8 (Box 87)
    - Carr, Virginia - fan mail to Robert Nathan, 1978-1982; 3 (Box 88)
    - Lehmann, Lotte - fan mail to Robert Nathan, 1949-1953; 2 (Box 88)
    - Correspondence regarding specific works, 1959-1967; 11 (Box 89)
      Works include "The Color of Evening", "The Devil with Love", "The Fair", Juliet in Mantua, "The Mallot Diaries", "The Married Man", The Snowflake and the Starfish, So Love Returns, A Star in the Wind, "Digging the Weans", and "The Wilderness Stone".
  - Writings
    - Robert Nathan diaries, 1925-1934, undated; 3 (Box 90)
    - Unpublished poems, circa 1946-1977 (Box 91)
      Works include Bitter Jewish Poems Rejected from "The Married Man," "Love Sonnet to Sidney Franklin", "Torpedo 8", and "The White Cliffs".
    - Unpublished poems (continued), 1981-1982; 2 (Box 91)
      Works include "Belief", "Fourscore", "From a Dying Fire", "Last Song", "Question", "Standing in the Need of Prayer", "To Anne - A Going Away Sonnet", and "To Anne - On April 5, 1981".
    - Verse, 1965-1969 (Box 91)
      Works include "Analist's Song", "A Critic's Garden of Verses", "Epithalamium: for Sandy, a Man of Courage", "Fiftieth Anniversary (Alfred and Blanche Knopf)", "For Lotte Lehmann", "My Turn Will Come", and "There Were Once Two Little Ants".
    - Verse (continued), 1980 (Box 91)
      Works include "Alone", "Harold Adamson", "Psalm 23a (Matilda)", "The Queen Mother's 80th Birthday", "The Swimmer", "To My Wife on Our 10th Anniversary", and "Tom Aston".
    - Verse (continued), 1965-1980; 2 (Box 91)
      Works include miscellaneous writings.
    - Unpublished verse, 1978-1979 (Box 91)
      Works include "At 85", "The Caged Bird", "Fireside Chat", "Happy Birthday", "I Did Not Know When I Was Old", "In the Firelight", and "June 1979".
    - Unpublished verse (continued), 1978-1979 (Box 91)
      Works include "A Memorial Service for Mankind", "The Oak", "The Runner" (also known as "Marathon"), "To Charles at 80" (Charles Bennet), "To My Darling Wife", "To My Valentine", and "Upon Her Shoulders Soft and White".
    - Unpublished verse (continued) (Box 91)
    - Prose, 1955-1959 (Box 91)
      Works include "Las Vegas - Miracle in the Desert", "The Lockets", "On Dane" - translation postscript to "Digging the Weans," and "The Trumpets".
    - Prose (continued), 1976-1977 (Box 91)
    - Prose (continued), 1978-1981; 2 (Box 91)
      Works include "The Absolute Egg", "A Curious Glory", "A Finer Point of Law", "The First Born Jew", "The Hate in Violence", "Letters to the Times", "Listening", and "Terror and Meism".
    - Prose (continued), 1978-1981; 2 (Box 92)
    - Prose (continued), undated (Box 92)
    - Unpublished prose, 1960-1975; 7 (Box 92)
    - Individual prose
      - "Another Look At Equal Rights" (Box 93)
      - "A Collect for Lovers" (Box 93)
      - "The Egalitarian Gas" (Box 93)
      - "The Elixir" (Box 93)
      - "A Feast of Freedom" (Box 93)
      - "Jezebel" (Box 93)
      - "Of Love and Lovers" (Box 93)
      - "On Leonard Wibberly" (Box 93)
      - The Summer Meadows (Box 93)
      - "Susan and the Stranger" (Box 93)
      - "The Fundamentalist" (Box 94)
      - "The Last Great Bard" (Box 94)
      - "Mephisto and the Mrs.", 3 (Box 94)
    - Speeches
      Arranged chronologically
      - Beethoven's Sixth, undated (Box 95)
      - Introducing Jack Smith, undated (Box 95)
      - Ladies Club at Pacific Palisades, undated (Box 95)
      - Ladies of the Federation, undated (Box 95)
      - Speech to "some ladies", undated (Box 95)
      - Speeches held at NBC, Boston Book Fair, New Jersey, Bennington, and Women's City Club, 1935-1943 (Box 95)
      - Speeches held at Poetry Society, Columbia University, Temple Rudolph, and P.E.N., 1935-1943 (Box 95)
      - Junior League speeches, 1945-1948 (Box 95)
      - Santa Barbara speech, 1956 (Box 95)
      - Speeches, 1957 (Box 95)
        Speeches include Paradox of Fantasy, Book and Author Luncheon ( A Star in the Wind ), A Plea for Slow Reading, and "Odds & Ends."
      - Palos Verdes Coffee House speech, 1958 (Box 95)
      - Knopf anniversary dinner, Brandeis University speeches, 1965 (Box 96)
      - Author Club speech, 1969 (Box 96)
      - Los Angeles Library Luncheon, answering speech, 1973 April 5 (Box 96)
      - The Booksellers speech, 1973 (Box 96)
      - Women of the University of Judaism regarding Leonard Wibberly, Max Showalter speech, 1973-1974 (Box 96)
      - Book Chamber of Ebell speech, 1974 October 23 (Box 96)
      - Speeches, 1975 (Box 96)
      - The Booksellers, UCLA Library Association Dinner speeches, 1978-1979 (Box 96)
      - Regarding Will Durant, Irving Stone (Author Club) speeches, 1980 (Box 96)
- Other Acquisitions, 1796-1985, undated; 8.05; (25 boxes)
  Organized into 9 subgroupings: May 1990 Acquisition; January 1974 Acquisition; October 1971 Acquisition; December 1965 Acquisition; 1964-1973 Acquisitions; July 1985 Acquisitions; November 1985 Acquisition; Printed Material; October 1985 Acquisition; and April 2008 Acquisition.
  This order largely reflects the order in which the earlier acquisitions listed below were formally accessioned following a 1990 bequest from Nathan's estate. This material, acquired between 1964 and 1985, had been shelved apart from the Za Nathan and Uncat Za Nathan groups.
  - May 1990 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 141
    - Clippings, 1960-1974 (Box 97)
    - Contract between Robert Nathan and The Selznick Studio for the motion picture Portrait of Jennie, 1944 January 21 (Box 97)
    - Invitation to a poetry reading by Robert Nathan and Archibald MacLeish, 1974 May 16 (Box 97)
    - TLS to Solomon, Joe, 1978 January 4 (Box 97)
    - Portrait of Jennie program, undated (Box 97)
    - "Susan and the Stranger" program, 1956 July (Box 97)
    - "Westways": printed version, electrostat copy, and fragment, undated (Box 97)
  - January 1974 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 161
    - "The Ice Maiden," typescript, corrected (Box 98)
    - Jezebel's Husband - changes made in August 1952, 2 (Box 98)
    - "Mephisto and the Mrs." - carbon typescript (Box 98)
    - Mia
      - Additions and rewrites (Box 98)
      - Author typescript (Box 98)
      - Carbon typescript (Box 98)
      - Secretary's copy with author corrections, 2 (Box 98)
      - Typist's copy with autograph notes (Box 98)
      - Typist's copy with autograph notes (continued) (Box 99)
    - So Love Returns
      - Attempted changes in opening (Box 99)
      - Typescript draft for Oskar Werner, 1968 November 24 (Box 99)
      - Work on screenplay with Oskar Werner, 3 (Box 99)
    - A Star in the Wind - screenplay (Box 99)
    - The Summer Meadows
      - Autograph and typescript drafts, 2 (Box 99)
      - False starts, 1972, undated; 4 (Box 100)
        Includes false starts from "The Elixir"
    - Later poems, letters to newspapers, etc. (Box 100)
    - Light verse, letter to "Butch", 1962-1963 (Box 100)
    - Slight pieces, poem from Room 514, 1970 chronicles, 1967-1970 (Box 100)
    - Verse, miscellaneous writings, 1968-1972; 2 (Box 100)
  - October 1971 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 162
    - Mia
      - First draft, typescript (Box 101)
      - Setting typescript, 2 (Box 101)
      - Page proofs, 2 (Box 101)
  - December 1965 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 163
    - "The Married Man" artwork
  - 1963-1973 Acquisitions
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 169
    - Indenture between various individuals and Simon Nathan, manuscript on parchment, 1796 May 16 (Box 102)
    - Correspondence
      - Feis, Herbert and Undine, 1921-1973, undated; 7 (Box 103)
      - Feis, Herbert, 1918-1980, undated; 4 (Box 103)
      - Feis, Herbert (continued), 1918-1980, undated; 4 (Box 104)
      - Feis, Undine, 1930-1954, undated; 2 (Box 104)
      - Kubie, Lawrence, 1953-1967 (Box 104)
    - Writings
      - "The Elixir" (Box 104)
      - Mia
        - Author typescript, 2 (Box 104)
        - Carbon typescript, 1969 (Box 104)
        - Typescript and carbon drafts, 2 (Box 105)
        - Autograph notes, 1968-1969; 3 (Box 105)
      - Autobiography
        - Author typescript, 2 (Box 105)
        - Autograph drafts, 2 (Box 105)
        - Replaced pages, 2 (Box 105)
        - Notes (Box 105)
      - False start for a novel, 1968 (Box 105)
      - Notes on false starts, 1959 (Box 105)
    - Clippings, 1920-1924 (Box 105)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 105)
  - July 1985 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 332
    - Bitker, Marjorie - correspondence, 1964-1985 (Box 106)
    - "Speak to God and Others" - typescript draft, 1982 (Box 106)
    - Clippings, 1962, 1985 (Box 106)
      Includes obituaries of Nathan
  - November 1982 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za MS 345
    - Correspondence
      - Robert Nathan to Marjorie Bitker, 1956-1982, undated; 24 (Box 107)
      - Marjorie Bitker to Robert Nathan, 1961-1982; 9 (Box 107)
      - Marjorie Bitker to Robert Nathan (continued), 1961-1982; 17 (Box 108)
      - Leslie Cross to Marjorie Bitker, 1961-1962 (Box 108)
      - Donald Gallup to Marjorie Bitker, 1962 May (Box 108)
      - Anna Lee Nathan to Marjorie Bitker, 1973 March 25 (Box 108)
      - Margaret Paley to Marjorie Bitker, 1961-1962 (Box 108)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 108)
  - Printed material: various acquisition dates
    Formerly classed as ZA N195 +1 and 2.
    - Clippings
      - Individual titles (Box 109)
      - "A Portrait of Robert Nathan" from the Milwaukee Journal, 1962 June 7 (Box 109)
      - "The Puppet Master", 1923-1924 (Box 109)
      - Unsorted clippings, 2 (Box 109)
    - Printed Ephemera
      - The Atlantic Monthly, 1920-1939; 3 (Box 109)
      - The Century Magazine, 1924 October (Box 110)
      - The Harvard Monthly, 1913-1914; 2 (Box 110)
      - The New Yorker (Box 110)
      - The Phillips Exeter Monthly, 1912; 2 (Box 110)
      - Saturday Review (Box 110)
      - Schribner's Magazine, 1927 September (Box 110)
      - Smart Set (Box 110)
      - Magazine pieces about Robert Nathan (Box 110)
      - Miscellaneous printed ephemera, 1921-1959 (Box 110)
      - Miscellaneous printed ephemera (continued), 1921-1959; 5 (Box 111)
  - October 1985 Acquisition
    Formerly classed as Uncat Za File 108
    - Sketch of President McKinley's funeral by Robert Nathan, 1901 September 19 (Box 111)
  - May 1991 Acquisition
    General
    Formerly classed as Uncat ZA MS 179
    - The Woodcutter's House, draft, manuscript and typescript (Box 122)
  - April 2008 Acquisition
    - Awards, 0.67; (2 boxes)
      - American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers: membership, circa 1943 (Box 112)
      - Academy of American Poets: Honorary Fellowship, circa 1972 (Box 112)
      - California Writers Guild: Award of Honor, circa 1960 (Box 112)
      - City of Los Angeles: Certificate of Achievement, circa 1981 (Box 112)
      - Authors Club: Member of the Year, 1980 (Box 112)
      - MGM: Box Office Blue Ribbon Award for screenplay "The Clock", 1945 June (Box 112)
      - National Film Society: Achievement in Cinema Award, 1982 (Box 113)
      - City of Los Angeles: Commendation, Sam Yorty, Mayor, 1973 April (Box 113)
      - City of Los Angeles: Proclamation, Tom Bradley, Mayor, 1974 January (Box 113)
      - City of Los Angeles: Raised Seal Plaque, Sam Yorty, Mayor, 1973 April (Box 113)
    - Scrapbooks, 1.75; (7 boxes)
      - "Mia; The Elixir ('70)", circa 1970 (Box 114 Oversize)
      - "The Enchanted Voyage; Winter in April", circa 1936 (Box 114 Oversize)
      - '42, circa 1942 (Box 115 Oversize)
      - "The Orchid; One More Spring", circa 1930 (Box 115 Oversize)
      - '43, circa 1943 (Box 116 Oversize)
      - "Winter in April '38 (cover missing)", circa 1938 (Box 116 Oversize)
      - "A Winter Tide", circa 1940 (Box 116 Oversize)
      - '43, circa 1943 (Box 117 Oversize)
      - They Went on Together; Tapiola's Brave Regiment ('41), circa 1941 (Box 117 Oversize)
      - "One More Spring (no front cover)", circa 1933-1935 (Box 118 Oversize)
      - "The Woodcutter's House; The Bishop's Wife; A Cedar Box; There is Another Heaven", circa 1928-1929 (Box 118 Oversize)
      - "Road of Ages (III); Autumn; Selected Poems", circa 1935-1936 (Box 119 Oversize)
      - "Road of Ages (II)", circa 1935 (Box 119 Oversize)
      - '47, circa 1947 (Box 119 Oversize)
      - Tapiola, circa 1938 (Box 120 Oversize)
      - "The Enchanted Voyage (I)", circa 1936 (Box 120 Oversize)
      - '47, circa 1947-1948 (Box 120 Oversize)
      - '49, circa 1949-1950 (Box 120 Oversize)
- Oversize, 0.25; (1 box)
  - "The Married Man" artwork (from December 1965 accession) (Box 121 Oversize)
  - Photographs, 1950, 1962; 3 (Box 121 Oversize)
  - Sheet music, 5 (Box 121 Oversize)